Introduction

Symfony [https://symfony.com/] is a reusable set of standalone, decoupled and cohesive PHP components that solve common web development problems.

Instead of using these low-level components, you can use the ready-to-be-used Symfony full-stack web framework, which is based on these components… or you can create your very own framework. This tutorial is about the latter.

Why would you Like to Create your Own Framework?

Why would you like to create your own framework in the first place? If you look around, everybody will tell you that it’s a bad thing to reinvent the wheel and that you’d better choose an existing framework and forget about creating your own altogether. Most of the time, they are right but there are a few good reasons to start creating your own framework:

To learn more about the low level architecture of modern web frameworks in general and about the Symfony full-stack framework internals in particular;

To create a framework tailored to your very specific needs (just be sure first that your needs are really specific);

To experiment creating a framework for fun (in a learn-and-throw-away approach);

To refactor an old/existing application that needs a good dose of recent web development best practices;

To prove the world that you can actually create a framework on your own (… but with little effort).

This tutorial will gently guide you through the creation of a web framework, one step at a time. At each step, you will have a fully-working framework that you can use as is or as a start for your very own. It will start with a simple framework and more features will be added with time. Eventually, you will have a fully-featured full-stack web framework.

And each step will be the occasion to learn more about some of the Symfony Components.

Many modern web frameworks advertise themselves as being MVC frameworks. This tutorial won’t talk about the MVC pattern, as the Symfony Components are able to create any type of frameworks, not just the ones that follow the MVC architecture. Anyway, if you have a look at the MVC semantics, this book is about how to create the Controller part of a framework. For the Model and the View, it really depends on your personal taste and you can use any existing third-party libraries (Doctrine, Propel or plain-old PDO for the Model; PHP or Twig for the View).

When creating a framework, following the MVC pattern is not the right goal. The main goal should be the Separation of Concerns; this is probably the only design pattern that you should really care about. The fundamental principles of the Symfony Components are focused on the HTTP specification. As such, the framework that you are going to create should be more accurately labelled as a HTTP framework or Request/Response framework.

Before You Start

Reading about how to create a framework is not enough. You will have to follow along and actually type all the examples included in this tutorial. For that, you need a recent version of PHP (5.5.9 or later is good enough), a web server (like Apache, nginx or PHP’s built-in web server), a good knowledge of PHP and an understanding of Object Oriented programming.

Ready to go? Read on!

Bootstrapping

Before you can even think of creating the first framework, you need to think about some conventions: where you will store the code, how you will name the classes, how you will reference external dependencies, etc.

To store your new framework, create a directory somewhere on your machine:

1
2

|

$ mkdir framework
$ cd framework

Dependency Management

To install the Symfony Components that you need for your framework, you are going to use Composer, a project dependency manager for PHP. If you don’t have it yet, download and install Composer [https://getcomposer.org/download/] now.

Our Project

Instead of creating our framework from scratch, we are going to write the same “application” over and over again, adding one abstraction at a time. Let’s start with the simplest web application we can think of in PHP:

// framework/index.php
$name = $_GET['name'];

printf('Hello %s', $name);

You can use the Symfony Local Web Server to test this great application in a browser (http://localhost:8000/index.php?name=Fabien):

1

|

$ symfony server:start

In the next chapter, we are going to introduce the HttpFoundation Component and see what it brings us.

The HttpFoundation Component

Before diving into the framework creation process, let’s first step back and let’s take a look at why you would like to use a framework instead of keeping your plain-old PHP applications as is. Why using a framework is actually a good idea, even for the simplest snippet of code and why creating your framework on top of the Symfony components is better than creating a framework from scratch.

Note

We won’t talk about the traditional benefits of using a framework when working on big applications with more than a few developers; the Internet has already plenty of good resources on that topic.

Even if the “application” we wrote in the previous chapter was simple enough, it suffers from a few problems:

// framework/index.php
$name = $_GET['name'];

printf('Hello %s', $name);

First, if the name query parameter is not defined in the URL query string, you will get a PHP warning; so let’s fix it:

// framework/index.php
$name = isset($_GET['name']) ? $_GET['name'] : 'World';

printf('Hello %s', $name);

Then, this application is not secure. Can you believe it? Even this simple snippet of PHP code is vulnerable to one of the most widespread Internet security issue, XSS (Cross-Site Scripting). Here is a more secure version:

$name = isset($_GET['name']) ? $_GET['name'] : 'World';

header('Content-Type: text/html; charset=utf-8');

printf('Hello %s', htmlspecialchars($name, ENT_QUOTES, 'UTF-8'));

Note

As you might have noticed, securing your code with htmlspecialchars is tedious and error prone. That’s one of the reasons why using a template engine like Twig [https://twig.symfony.com/], where auto-escaping is enabled by default, might be a good idea (and explicit escaping is also less painful with the usage of a simple e filter).

As you can see for yourself, the simple code we had written first is not that simple anymore if we want to avoid PHP warnings/notices and make the code more secure.

Beyond security, this code can be complex to test. Even if there is not much to test, it strikes me that writing unit tests for the simplest possible snippet of PHP code is not natural and feels ugly. Here is a tentative PHPUnit unit test for the above code:

// framework/test.php
use PHPUnit\Framework\TestCase;

class IndexTest extends TestCase
{
    public function testHello()
    {
        $_GET['name'] = 'Fabien';

        ob_start();
        include 'index.php';
        $content = ob_get_clean();

        $this->assertEquals('Hello Fabien', $content);
    }
}

Note

If our application were just slightly bigger, we would have been able to find even more problems. If you are curious about them, read the Symfony versus Flat PHP chapter of the book.

At this point, if you are not convinced that security and testing are indeed two very good reasons to stop writing code the old way and adopt a framework instead (whatever adopting a framework means in this context), you can stop reading this book now and go back to whatever code you were working on before.

Note

Using a framework should give you more than just security and testability, but the more important thing to keep in mind is that the framework you choose must allow you to write better code faster.

Going OOP with the HttpFoundation Component

Writing web code is about interacting with HTTP. So, the fundamental principles of our framework should be around the HTTP specification [https://tools.ietf.org/wg/httpbis/].

The HTTP specification describes how a client (a browser for instance) interacts with a server (our application via a web server). The dialog between the client and the server is specified by well-defined messages, requests and responses: the client sends a request to the server and based on this request, the server returns a response.

In PHP, the request is represented by global variables ($_GET, $_POST, $_FILE, $_COOKIE, $_SESSION…) and the response is generated by functions (echo, header, setcookie, …).

The first step towards better code is probably to use an Object-Oriented approach; that’s the main goal of the Symfony HttpFoundation component: replacing the default PHP global variables and functions by an Object-Oriented layer.

To use this component, add it as a dependency of the project:

1

|

$ composer require symfony/http-foundation

Running this command will also automatically download the Symfony HttpFoundation component and install it under the vendor/ directory. A composer.json and a composer.lock file will be generated as well, containing the new requirement.

Class Autoloading

When installing a new dependency, Composer also generates a vendor/autoload.php file that allows any class to be autoloaded [https://www.php.net/autoload]. Without autoloading, you would need to require the file where a class is defined before being able to use it. But thanks to PSR-4 [https://www.php-fig.org/psr/psr-4/], we can just let Composer and PHP do the hard work for us.

Now, let’s rewrite our application by using the Request and the Response classes:

// framework/index.php
require_once __DIR__.'/vendor/autoload.php';

use Symfony\Component\HttpFoundation\Request;
use Symfony\Component\HttpFoundation\Response;

$request = Request::createFromGlobals();

$name = $request->get('name', 'World');

$response = new Response(sprintf('Hello %s', htmlspecialchars($name, ENT_QUOTES, 'UTF-8')));

$response->send();

The createFromGlobals() method creates a Request object based on the current PHP global variables.

The send() method sends the Response object back to the client (it first outputs the HTTP headers followed by the content).

Tip

Before the send() call, we should have added a call to the prepare() method ($response->prepare($request);) to ensure that our Response were compliant with the HTTP specification. For instance, if we were to call the page with the HEAD method, it would remove the content of the Response.

The main difference with the previous code is that you have total control of the HTTP messages. You can create whatever request you want and you are in charge of sending the response whenever you see fit.

Note

We haven’t explicitly set the Content-Type header in the rewritten code as the charset of the Response object defaults to UTF-8.

With the Request class, you have all the request information at your fingertips thanks to a nice and simple API:

// the URI being requested (e.g. /about) minus any query parameters
$request->getPathInfo();

// retrieve GET and POST variables respectively
$request->query->get('foo');
$request->request->get('bar', 'default value if bar does not exist');

// retrieve SERVER variables
$request->server->get('HTTP_HOST');

// retrieves an instance of UploadedFile identified by foo
$request->files->get('foo');

// retrieve a COOKIE value
$request->cookies->get('PHPSESSID');

// retrieve an HTTP request header, with normalized, lowercase keys
$request->headers->get('host');
$request->headers->get('content-type');

$request->getMethod();    // GET, POST, PUT, DELETE, HEAD
$request->getLanguages(); // an array of languages the client accepts

You can also simulate a request:

$request = Request::create('/index.php?name=Fabien');

With the Response class, you can tweak the response:

$response = new Response();

$response->setContent('Hello world!');
$response->setStatusCode(200);
$response->headers->set('Content-Type', 'text/html');

// configure the HTTP cache headers
$response->setMaxAge(10);

Tip

To debug a response, cast it to a string; it will return the HTTP representation of the response (headers and content).

Last but not least, these classes, like every other class in the Symfony code, have been audited [https://symfony.com/blog/symfony2-security-audit] for security issues by an independent company. And being an Open-Source project also means that many other developers around the world have read the code and have already fixed potential security problems. When was the last time you ordered a professional security audit for your home-made framework?

Even something as simple as getting the client IP address can be insecure:

if ($myIp === $_SERVER['REMOTE_ADDR']) {
    // the client is a known one, so give it some more privilege
}

It works perfectly fine until you add a reverse proxy in front of the production servers; at this point, you will have to change your code to make it work on both your development machine (where you don’t have a proxy) and your servers:

if ($myIp === $_SERVER['HTTP_X_FORWARDED_FOR'] || $myIp === $_SERVER['REMOTE_ADDR']) {
    // the client is a known one, so give it some more privilege
}

Using the Request::getClientIp() method would have given you the right behavior from day one (and it would have covered the case where you have chained proxies):

$request = Request::createFromGlobals();

if ($myIp === $request->getClientIp()) {
    // the client is a known one, so give it some more privilege
}

And there is an added benefit: it is secure by default. What does it mean? The $_SERVER['HTTP_X_FORWARDED_FOR'] value cannot be trusted as it can be manipulated by the end user when there is no proxy. So, if you are using this code in production without a proxy, it becomes trivially easy to abuse your system. That’s not the case with the getClientIp() method as you must explicitly trust your reverse proxies by calling setTrustedProxies():

Request::setTrustedProxies(['10.0.0.1']);

if ($myIp === $request->getClientIp()) {
    // the client is a known one, so give it some more privilege
}

So, the getClientIp() method works securely in all circumstances. You can use it in all your projects, whatever the configuration is, it will behave correctly and safely. That’s one of the goals of using a framework. If you were to write a framework from scratch, you would have to think about all these cases by yourself. Why not using a technology that already works?

Note

If you want to learn more about the HttpFoundation component, you can have a look at the Symfony\Component\HttpFoundation API or read its dedicated documentation.

Believe it or not but we have our first framework. You can stop now if you want. Using just the Symfony HttpFoundation component already allows you to write better and more testable code. It also allows you to write code faster as many day-to-day problems have already been solved for you.

As a matter of fact, projects like Drupal have adopted the HttpFoundation component; if it works for them, it will probably work for you. Don’t reinvent the wheel.

I’ve almost forgotten to talk about one added benefit: using the HttpFoundation component is the start of better interoperability between all frameworks and applications using it [https://symfony.com/components/HttpFoundation] (like Symfony [https://symfony.com/], Drupal 8 [https://www.drupal.org/], phpBB 3 [https://www.phpbb.com/], Laravel [https://laravel.com/] and ezPublish 5 [https://ez.no/], and more [https://symfony.com/components/HttpFoundation]).

The HttpKernel Component: The HttpKernel Class

If you were to use our framework right now, you would probably have to add support for custom error messages. We do have 404 and 500 error support but the responses are hardcoded in the framework itself. Making them customizable is straightforward though: dispatch a new event and listen to it. Doing it right means that the listener has to call a regular controller. But what if the error controller throws an exception? You will end up in an infinite loop. There should be an easier way, right?

Enter the HttpKernel class. Instead of solving the same problem over and over again and instead of reinventing the wheel each time, the HttpKernel class is a generic, extensible and flexible implementation of HttpKernelInterface.

This class is very similar to the framework class we have written so far: it dispatches events at some strategic points during the handling of the request, it uses a controller resolver to choose the controller to dispatch the request to, and as an added bonus, it takes care of edge cases and provides great feedback when a problem arises.

Here is the new framework code:

// example.com/src/Simplex/Framework.php
namespace Simplex;

use Symfony\Component\HttpKernel\HttpKernel;

class Framework extends HttpKernel
{
}

And the new front controller:

// example.com/web/front.php
require_once __DIR__.'/../vendor/autoload.php';

use Symfony\Component\EventDispatcher\EventDispatcher;
use Symfony\Component\HttpFoundation\Request;
use Symfony\Component\HttpFoundation\RequestStack;
use Symfony\Component\HttpFoundation\Response;
use Symfony\Component\HttpKernel;
use Symfony\Component\Routing;

$request = Request::createFromGlobals();
$requestStack = new RequestStack();
$routes = include __DIR__.'/../src/app.php';

$context = new Routing\RequestContext();
$matcher = new Routing\Matcher\UrlMatcher($routes, $context);

$controllerResolver = new HttpKernel\Controller\ControllerResolver();
$argumentResolver = new HttpKernel\Controller\ArgumentResolver();

$dispatcher = new EventDispatcher();
$dispatcher->addSubscriber(new HttpKernel\EventListener\RouterListener($matcher, $requestStack));

$framework = new Simplex\Framework($dispatcher, $controllerResolver, $requestStack, $argumentResolver);

$response = $framework->handle($request);
$response->send();

RouterListener is an implementation of the same logic we had in our framework: it matches the incoming request and populates the request attributes with route parameters.

Our code is now much more concise and surprisingly more robust and more powerful than ever. For instance, use the built-in ErrorListener to make your error management configurable:

$errorHandler = function (Symfony\Component\ErrorHandler\Exception\FlattenException $exception) {
    $msg = 'Something went wrong! ('.$exception->getMessage().')';

    return new Response($msg, $exception->getStatusCode());
};
$dispatcher->addSubscriber(new HttpKernel\EventListener\ErrorListener($errorHandler));

ErrorListener gives you a FlattenException instance instead of the thrown Exception or Error instance to ease exception manipulation and display. It can take any valid controller as an exception handler, so you can create an ErrorController class instead of using a Closure:

$listener = new HttpKernel\EventListener\ErrorListener(
    'Calendar\Controller\ErrorController::exception'
);
$dispatcher->addSubscriber($listener);

The error controller reads as follows:

// example.com/src/Calendar/Controller/ErrorController.php
namespace Calendar\Controller;

use Symfony\Component\ErrorHandler\Exception\FlattenException;
use Symfony\Component\HttpFoundation\Response;

class ErrorController
{
    public function exception(FlattenException $exception)
    {
        $msg = 'Something went wrong! ('.$exception->getMessage().')';

        return new Response($msg, $exception->getStatusCode());
    }
}

Voilà! Clean and customizable error management without efforts. And if your ErrorController throws an exception, HttpKernel will handle it nicely.

In chapter two, we talked about the Response::prepare() method, which ensures that a Response is compliant with the HTTP specification. It is probably a good idea to always call it just before sending the Response to the client; that’s what the ResponseListener does:

$dispatcher->addSubscriber(new HttpKernel\EventListener\ResponseListener('UTF-8'));

If you want out of the box support for streamed responses, subscribe to StreamedResponseListener:

$dispatcher->addSubscriber(new HttpKernel\EventListener\StreamedResponseListener());

And in your controller, return a StreamedResponse instance instead of a Response instance.

Tip

Read the Built-in Symfony Events reference to learn more about the events dispatched by HttpKernel and how they allow you to change the flow of a request.

Now, let’s create a listener, one that allows a controller to return a string instead of a full Response object:

class LeapYearController
{
    public function index(Request $request, $year)
    {
        $leapYear = new LeapYear();
        if ($leapYear->isLeapYear($year)) {
            return 'Yep, this is a leap year! ';
        }

        return 'Nope, this is not a leap year.';
    }
}

To implement this feature, we are going to listen to the kernel.view event, which is triggered just after the controller has been called. Its goal is to convert the controller return value to a proper Response instance, but only if needed:

// example.com/src/Simplex/StringResponseListener.php
namespace Simplex;

use Symfony\Component\EventDispatcher\EventSubscriberInterface;
use Symfony\Component\HttpFoundation\Response;
use Symfony\Component\HttpKernel\Event\ViewEvent;

class StringResponseListener implements EventSubscriberInterface
{
    public function onView(ViewEvent $event)
    {
        $response = $event->getControllerResult();

        if (is_string($response)) {
            $event->setResponse(new Response($response));
        }
    }

    public static function getSubscribedEvents()
    {
        return ['kernel.view' => 'onView'];
    }
}

The code is simple because the kernel.view event is only triggered when the controller return value is not a Response and because setting the response on the event stops the event propagation (our listener cannot interfere with other view listeners).

Don’t forget to register it in the front controller:

$dispatcher->addSubscriber(new Simplex\StringResponseListener());

Note

If you forget to register the subscriber, HttpKernel will throw an exception with a nice message: The controller must return a response (Nope, this is not a leap year. given)..

At this point, our whole framework code is as compact as possible and it is mainly composed of an assembly of existing libraries. Extending is a matter of registering event listeners/subscribers.

Hopefully, you now have a better understanding of why the simple looking HttpKernelInterface is so powerful. Its default implementation, HttpKernel, gives you access to a lot of cool features, ready to be used out of the box, with no efforts. And because HttpKernel is actually the code that powers the Symfony framework, you have the best of both worlds: a custom framework, tailored to your needs, but based on a rock-solid and well maintained low-level architecture that has been proven to work for many websites; a code that has been audited for security issues and that has proven to scale well.